hi welcome to tear down Tuesday we love
retro computers here on the eev blog
doesn't get as much retro as this little
know puppy everyone knows about the
Apple Macintosh of course absolute
classic and well they still it's still
around today but not many people except
your uh computer offici AOS know about
the Apple Lisa and this was Apple's
first graphical user interface machine
it pre dates the Macintosh this one came
out in January
1983 so it's over 30 years old fantastic
and I've got one I think they're pretty
rare here in Australia they're over
100,000 made which it was pretty much a
failure um they expected to uh sell a
lot more of these things but
unfortunately it was originally released
at
$10,000 that was $
19983 and just the price of it even
though the hardware and the graphical
use user interface and everything else
was pretty impressive H it was just too
darn expensive so it died what a shame
now rumor has it this thing cost Apple
about $50 million to develop and it
actually took them about 5 years to do
it they originally started developing
this in around 1978 designed to be like
a the replacement for the Apple 2 which
of course was the killer machine of the
day and uh the graphical user interface
technology of this of course comes from
uh 1979 after Apple were allowed in to
visit the uh Park and see the uh Alto
and uh their graphical user interface
technology the mouse and everything else
so unfortunately I don't have a keyboard
with this and I don't have the mouse
which was an absolute killer thing for
this uh at the time everyone raved about
The Mouse and the graphical user
interface uh largely well the concept
was stolen from Park but hey credit
where it's due to the the Apple team
they actually uh developed that then uh
they basically developed their own uh
graphical user interface uh system and
you know bought it to commercial reality
whereas the park Hardware wasn't really
uh commercial it was just sort of
prototype they never really uh took it
to market now of course this was uh
famously Steve Jobs baby and it was
named after Steve Jobs's baby Lisa
that's where the name comes from which
he finally uh admitted uh later in the
game a lot of people came up with what
you know ideas for what the acronym
actually uh stood for but no it was
named after his daughter Lisa and it's a
pretty sexy looking machine check it out
I just you know even today I think it
still holds up um you obviously modern
computers don't look like this but it
still is has a sort of beautiful quality
to it I really like the design of this
thing Beauty so a lot of the uh credit
for the hardware in this thing generally
goes to Wayne Uh rosin who was the uh
key architect behind the hardware in
this puppy which is what we're going to
take a look at I most likely can't get
it booted I don't think this thing works
as we'll see in the back here I've
already like just taken off the back
panel had a look and it doesn't look
that terrific so yeah I don't know if to
get it back up and working it may
require significant effort no idea if
there's actually a hard drive in here at
all so anyway this is tear down Tuesday
and you know we say here on the EV blog
don't turn it on take it apart and yes I
know what all you afficionados are going
to say Dave you're pulling a Swifty this
isn't the original Apple Lisa well no
it's not this is actually the Lisa 2 uh
which came out a year later January 1984
but it's damn close to the original the
only thing they changed was that um
basically they changed to the uh the
Sony 400k uh 3 and 1/2 in micro floppy
here cuz the original Lisa had two 5 and
1/4 in drives they were code named
Twiggy uh and they were apparently
horribly unreliable so they just dropped
that and they had to use speal special
discs so apparently they were horribly
unreliable drives those twiggies so it
made sense to uh change over to the Sony
Micro Drive which was pretty much the
duck's guts at the time and if you look
under the bottom here which has room for
the keyboard here how it's all recessed
in and that is a very nice design aspect
of this I really like um and it's got
nothing but a big clunk in power switch
under there you know you can't easily uh
hit that very nice and the keyboard Port
as well and just for the Apple fan boys
there's the money
shot and by the way this thing weighs a
bloody ton and on the back here we've
got uh what looks like a reset switch
but um I can't press that at all it
ain't working like a switch we've got a
video out with which is uh kind of weird
considering it has video building we've
got a parallel port we' got our Mouse
port and two serial ports as well and uh
it looks like it's only 120 volt AC
Supply only so yeah I'm not going to be
able to power it up without a Main's
Transformer to drop the voltage and
looks like we got brightness and sink
controls as well for the monitor here so
little bit crusty another Apple logo for
the Fanboys and credits also Al got to
go to Robert parator as well apparently
he uh worked on the hardware too was one
of the uh key designers of this thing by
the way yes it does use a Motorola
68,000 processor at a screaming 5 mahz
so not as fast as the original Macintosh
now apparently um these things are
really uh sort of like modular and
designed to be easily open and
apparently there's two clips on the
bottom here I haven't never tried this
but apparently
you're supposed to be able
to
lift there we go supposed to be able to
lift that out a no hard drive ripped off
this is where the hard drive is supposed
to go and what
what and there's the Sony micro floppy
and as you can see it has seen better
days lots of rust and corrosion on there
and it's going to get worse when we take
a look inside this is not a prime
example of an apple leaser unfortunately
and for those playing along at home here
is the serial number there's an Apple
net number as well and it was man
there's a manufacturer date but I have
no idea what that means now one
interesting feature is that here's the
front panel that comes off got ourselves
a micro switch there to detect whether
or not somebody's taken off the front
panel and apparently these things would
shut down if you took off the front or
the rear panels there's the original
Bill plate on the bottom it's the model
number
a603 made in the USA USA USA and uh it
has memory option whatever that is but
this thing uh the Apple the Lisa 2 came
standard with 1 Mega memory now you will
see a lot of uh rust and corrosion
inside this thing as we saw on the Sony
floppy drive here but all the uh like
all the aluminium metal work here really
looks in good Nick um nothing wrong with
that at all like it just was built
yesterday
yeah look at some of the corrosion on
the cereal Port connector there but
that's not uncommon for uh machines of
this vintage I did get this one uh from
near the beaches near the northern
beaches in uh Sydney so yeah not the
best environment with the uh saltwater
air and to get the back panel off you
just do these thumb screws here and
bingo Bob's your uncle we're in like
Flynn look at
that look down here look at the
corrosion on that card Edge connector oh
man I haven't seen anything that bad in
a long time that is just awful that may
be like well I'm not going to say
unrepairable but geez that is pretty
awful anyway we have to give it a clean
up and uh see what we can do with that
but this has bugger all chance of
working and then we've got four backup
batteries there well they've seen better
days oh
yuck and there's our three expansion
slots there and they're rather unusual
in that they're uh not very deep but
they're as tall as the machine so rather
unusual form factor expansion cards but
it makes sense of course given their
overall system design and there's the
main uh rum for this thing and you're
probably wondering who is Sun
remarketing Inc well it turns out that
there were a reseller uh back in the day
and they you know sold uh Apple
computers and older Apple Computers as
well and uh they tried they were very
obviously very keen on this uh Lisa and
uh did lots of like aftermarket
development for it and things like that
so maybe they've customized this rob a
little bit now I said this thing was
modular and that doesn't just extend to
the front and rear panels all of this uh
circuitry all this card cage because
this is just the io card at the back
we're going to all the system IO we're
going to have the uh processor board
behind that we've got a base board and
it's all supposed to just pull out and
that's why they've presumably why
they've got a metal bar here and I'm
going
to it's supposed to pull it it's
supposed to pull
out um yeah could be a bit Rusty it's
giving it's
giving yep there we go and this is some
clever
clever system design I like that check
it out we got ourselves a total of four
boards plus obviously uh memory boards
there's our main processor there's the
big beast 68,000 up there and uh and
plus the baseboard that's a really nice
designed card cage I really love that
thumbs up to whoever worked on that one
and just look at the attention to detail
on this car cage look they've gone to
the effort to silk screen the uh labels
in here two memory cards of course the
CPU and the io and they've color coded
them brilliant you can see that
basically nothing has changed on the
Lisa 2 here these are all using you know
the copyright 982 boards here so same
with the uh CPU one as well so uh really
essentially no difference they just
change the drives over and just sort of
change the marketing spec of the thing
and it seems like this one might have
the latest in quote marks uh firmware in
this thing look 1985 and for all you
68,000 Fanboys out there here it is oh
isn't it beautiful in that huge dip
package socketed of course in a crappy
uh dual WIP contact UM socket um date
code 21st week 83 and as I said before
this board is like
82 vintage and there's other chips on
here which are around about 83 vintage
so yeah this thing um was manufactured
in the time that they or round about the
time that they uh manufactured the Lisa
1 so this is a Lisa 2 but as I said it's
basically the same machine and you bet
your ass we've got a triple 5 timer oh
but it's twice as good it's the 556
awesome and there's the crystal on it uh
doesn't say what uh speed but the
processor operated at 5 MHz which was uh
much less than the than the first uh Mac
which ran at about eight or something
like that so yeah it was a pretty
sluggish machine with its complex
operating system as fantastic as the OS
art was and groundbreaking for its time
it was just apparently very very
sluggish and we've got ourselves a
classic uh four layer board construction
here very typical of the day of course
all the chips pretty much uh lined up in
rows the uh top side of the board has
all the traces and most of the traces
running in this direction cuz this is
how you routed these boards back in the
day um and of course ground plane and uh
Power plane and on the other side of
course you see all the other tracers
running in this direction like this so
it was just much easier to Route um it
could have been routed by hand it uh I
think it probably was um although they
did have the auto routing uh algorithms
to actually do these uh boards it was a
you know a fairly common task back in
the day to Auto rout these but I think
somebody took a bit of pride in this one
and uh actually hand laid that out and
the board was made in Singapore that
might have just been the uh be board I
it could have very well been uh stuffed
um which is the technical term it really
is um in the US I'm not sure but uh yeah
probably the blank board uh made in
Singapore and I am really concerned with
the oxidization on this board I've
really got to clean this up quick smart
but yeah it's it's not in great
condition let me tell you we still have
the odd bodge there we go um we got a
pin there obviously needed a cap the
ground uh yeah some sort of to just to
take the edge off that sucker we've uh
presumably got some sort of uh gal or
Pal array under there did giveaway that
it's got the um a part number on it but
the majority of the other chips are just
um you know offthe shelf uh Jelly Bean
um 74 series and just below the CPU
there we've got a little bit of uh
memory so I'm not sure what they're uh
not sure what they're doing there but
anyway most of the other chips we've got
a mix of uh all standard 74 series Jelly
Bean logic we've got um LS Series chips
nicely silk screen of course we got F
series uh we've got ALS down here we've
got ourselves some S Series logic so
that was fairly typical of the day to
mix and match your uh logic families
like that for just you know like you use
the 74f for the fast stuff obviously
they coupled that into the memory there
they decide to use F and for the lower
uh speed stuff in interfacing they use
um LS or they might use uh you know
slightly faster ALS and of course you
had the decoupling uh spread across the
board like this there we go a couple of
axial caps just you know not quite one
per chip you know they might be sharing
one per two chips in the processor might
have one up near it here but that's uh
about it for the decoupling cuz this
didn't run particularly fast and also
with the huge ground plane on this thing
you'd get a fair bit of capacitance
between uh you get a fair bit of
distributed capacitance on the ground
plane as well that was fairly common for
the day you could pretty much get away
with you could probably remove half
those Caps or you know a good majority
of them the thing could probably still
work now back over to this IO board now
and uh this is pretty fancy pancy look
at this you can see it's got its own
ground plane this is something you don't
often find on here they've got a
switching regulator with a 4193 on there
there's the big ass inductor they've got
the output filter cap for that and um
that's you know I don't know what rail
voltage they're generating there but uh
yeah they obviously needed a bit more
efficiency than what a uh a regular
regulator could provide or maybe they're
uh you know stepping it up maybe it's a
boost I'm not even sure of the uh
configuration there and we' got some
bodges and mod wires on here look
running all over the place to this uh 74
LS couple of pins there we go absolute
classic stuff I love it we got another
bodge cap down in here obviously had to
take the edge off that pin and uh you
know quite a few mods on here and we got
our custom Apple uh cops chip here 1981
so pretty ancient look at that look at
that corrosion oh my goodness is there
any anything left under that probably I
don't know
but M colorful crusty stuff under the
switch M look at that yum yum well there
you go that might fairly definitively uh
date this uh be board too with the 21st
week 84 so that's relatively late
actually and by the way if you're
wondering what these uh numbers across
here and these letters these are grid
coordinates this was fairly common back
in the day so that the uh service manual
could go well replace the chip at 11d
like that and bingo that' be that one
and if you hold it up to the light there
you go you can actually see through that
and uh this is a double-sided board
there's no uh ground plane in there so
they saved a fair bit of cost they
didn't need it like they did on the uh
main processor board and the keyboard
and parallel port controllers here these
are the 6522 via the standard uh IO
interface chip for the 65 2 processor
even though this is not a 6502 processor
based machine it's a Motorola
68,000 um you know totally different
architecture still you can reuse these
sort of interface chips no problems at
all and the serial Port up here is
controlled by the Xylo 8530 so once
again this was designed for the z80 um
like a Serial interface controller but
just like the 6502 V you can reuse these
things in pretty much any processor
architect Ure and that's what they
decided to do they were familiar with
them and just reuse it but they are
their own individually masked romed uh
processors just to handle those single
tasks and we've got ourselves a 6504
here I'm not sure what task that one's
actually running got ourselves a gal
here but most of the other stuff on here
is as before standard 74 series logic
and by the way the Lisa had very
Advanced copy protection for its day
pretty horrendous actually if you think
uh you know DRM is a pain in the ass
these days each machine had an
individual serial number programmed into
it I'm not sure uh where it is it's got
to be either a gal or a uh ROM somewhere
but an individual serial number
programmed into each machine which would
then be written onto the original
software disc when you ran it for the
first time so when you got your software
for the thing you could only register
and run it on your leasa machine so if
you're uh you know if you replaced your
Hardware H your software doesn't work
anymore any more and you couldn't sell
the software or anything so pretty
horrendous um you know I mean if this
machine actually got popular no one
would have stood for that in fact you
could say it was sort of destined not to
become popular even if it was affordable
because of that horrendous uh digital
Rights Management on the thing and
locking that software in on the original
discs but hey people are clever you know
they found ways around all the copy
protection schemes back in the day so
I'm no doubt uh somebody would have
found a way around this but because it
wasn't popular I don't think anyone
bothered does anyone know and here are
our two memory boards and they're
slightly different I mean this one here
has your traditional green solder mask
on it but this one here looks like yeah
different color so sort of manufactured
um maybe in a different Factory or a
different time certainly a different uh
batch process and the memory chips are
actually different same type but from
different manufacturers and it's
separated into the lower um bite and the
upper bite I believe these boards are
total of 500 and uh well 512k words
because it's a 16bit machine or 1
Megabyte of memory and but that was a
lot back in the day one Meg was W once
again made in Singapore looks like the
44th week 1983 this one and still made
in Singapore yet again but much older
39th week 84 so like a whole year
difference between these uh two boards
so uh you've got to wonder like a yeah
was this machine like a you know
aftermarket upgraded or something like
that not entirely sure but yeah there's
a huge difference between them so
obviously not probably not uh Factory
original uh boards like fitted when the
machine was originally bought and these
look for all the world like the uh be
board manufacturer markings here so
we've got ourselves Astro so is that the
uh name of the company that made this
one and uh
senina uh there so if anyone's got any
detail on the those companies but maybe
they're long on I don't know who know
well they could be still around making
boards who knows but as with all these
boards in the Apple Lisa they're all
branded like the processor board the io
board and these boards they're all uh
got a date of 1982 on there so that's
they would have been uh laid out and on
the older board check it out we have
apple branded mosfet dams here these are
the MK 4564 n-20 these are 200 nond 64k
by one bit and they're they were
manufactured 30th week 83 by mosc so
yeah apple ordered enough of these they
got their logo on them that's common and
the other board from 84 these are
Hatachi these are
hm64 48 64s um and -3 so they 300C jobs
anyway got the little Apple logo on
there and assembled in the USA and we've
got nine of these chips per Bank look at
that so obviously we had a uh parody bit
there cuz they own you know to make up a
bite you won cuz these are buy these are
one bit chips so you really only need
eight of them but they've got a ninth
one there so that must be for uh parody
I'm presuming and so each Bank of those
is 64k so 64 28 and got eight of those
total so this is actually a 512 uh K
board so the total system memory on the
Lisa was 1 Meg and I believe well this
Lisa 2 was sold standard with one Mega
memory so it would have been populated
with two of these boards but it was
capable of going up to 2 Meg but I don't
know if um anyone ever sold boards that
allowed it to be expanded up to 2 Meg at
least uh not possibly not Apple maybe a
third party and what's left in this card
cage well it's just Prett pretty sad
looking isn't it um there's not much in
we've got one chip down here in a socket
and uh looks like we have a couple of
inductors and caps in there for the
mouse Port that's some um RFI uh stuff
so and a couple of dip switches down
here for this seral and they look really
really crusty and oh look at the
corrosion on the contacts and oh they
they are pretty colors though and
there's the liser expansion bus three
slots and uh looks like we have a card
ejector of some description here and
then going into the main shazzy there
that looks like the video output uh
connector so it's just got uh three
wires just hard to see in there it's a
bit dark but uh yeah just the wires are
going off to the uh CRT in there and uh
then we've got ourselves the uh disc
drive connector and it's seen better
days the contacts it all needs thorough
cleaning as well and that just goes off
to a ribbon into the uh hard drive
controller and apparently it was pretty
intelligent for the day it would map out
bad sectors and uh do stuff like that I
mean we take it for granted these days
but that was pretty advanced stuff back
then and once again with the modular
nature of this thing check it out the
power
supply switching of course just uh pops
out there we go we got some big um High
current contacts down there very nice a
data power Inc actually did that there
we go December 20th
1984 um they're in Orange County
California fantastic so that's made in
the US as well got ourselves a little
single-sided Riser controller board here
that might have been common across
different uh products perhaps but um
it's it's okay you know for the day look
at all the uh look at all the hot snot
down in there it's well it's not hot
snot it's actually uh uh sastic um type
stuff and uh just holding a few of the
wi down you know and that's not too
shabby look they've got the spaces down
here on the diode so they're lifting
those off to get the air flow and the
extra uh heat sinking of the leads down
there so it's it's not too you know it's
it's okay it does look a bit how you're
doing but I I don't mind it at all
especially for the uh for the Vintage
there we go we got some extra heat
sinking on these doodes down here
they've put them on that uh plate just
to heat sink those and uh little space
are in there they're just it's a bit
Loosey Goosey but it's does the business
and I was wondering where the micro
switch was for the back panel there it
is there but I'm led to believe that the
Lisa has like a um soft shutdown
function even the power button which I
said was a big clunking uh power switch
before on the front panel apparently
it's still a soft button and the Lisa
would actually uh gracefully shut down
um and then uh reboot to where it was
which was pretty Advanced for the day
and uh maybe if you removed the uh front
and back panels This is the back panel
one so that would interrupt the
processor and uh gracefully shut the
machine down so you you certainly can't
uh Power this thing up you've got to
override these uh switches if you want
to pair it up with the uh back covers
front or back covers off and by the way
yes this isn't quite the original color
it has yellowed with age which is very
typical of the Machines of the day it's
the bromide that was used in the plastic
you can actually rejuvenate uh these
things not terribly easy but you can
rejuvenate and get that original uh
beige uh color look back and the color
should be reasonably accurate here on
the video I have color balance my video
camera so this is you know not exactly
Factory original color but very common
and unfortunately on this processor
board even after trying to clean this up
like really heavy scraping with uh a
conductive brush and isopropanol alcohol
look the pads are just eaten away on
this card Edge connector here and and
that Gunk is just caked on there and
there's just oh I mean you know
ultimately it's repairable but gez you
got to put a lot of work into fixing
something like this so unfortunately um
those batteries have uh have done their
business and um ruined this poor
innocent processor board what a shame M
look what we have to deal with here and
H like that's like the rot has started
on these connectors
and yeah I think this one is uh be
Beyond economical repair that looks like
a capacitor H used to be wow look at
that and even the batteries are branded
Apple check it out assembled in Mexico
and you can see the rot has started
setting under the soar mask there and
well yeah that's just starting to eat
away the copper under there in many
places on the board like this check it
out and that's uh yeah that's only going
to get worse with time unless you got in
there and H thoroughly stripped it all
down and put in new traces and well yeah
this thing is uh pretty much gone and
here's the Sony floppy Drive controller
it's called the light adapter and there
is the only Lisa logo that we've
actually found inside this thing so so
far there it is silk screened onto the
board the other boards don't have it at
all and there's not a huge amount on
there there's just some 74 series chips
and a 5. 068 mahz crystal there it is
and the Lisa 2 also has this extra
socket here for the AMD am
9512 floating Point math coprocessor
it's a 64-bit job and it's you know it
doesn't have a huge amount of
functionality it's only got your basic
operations but hey a math co-processor
was was not too bad in the day but by
the time this one uh was out I think
like the um intel 8087 was around and it
was it was better and sort of yeah this
one wasn't that popular so it's not even
fited to this not even sure if any of
the uh Lisa software took advantage of
it now this is actually a Lisa 2 machine
as as opposed to the uh different Lisa
210 which had the built-in uh 10m hard
drive in it and I probably should have
known that before I even open it because
it does have uh the Lisa 2 had the
parallel port connector on the back for
connecting over to the hard drive module
whereas the 2/10 they uh redesigned this
motherboard and uh left out the uh
parallel connector on the back oh and in
case you're wondering about the Glorious
screen a whopping 720x 360 resolution
monochrome only of course but hey this
was actually considered a high
resolution screen back in its day so not
too bad at all and at the bottom of for
the CRT after you uh remove the main
cover plate on here we can see we got
our system speaker and you can probably
just see the uh part number on the tube
down in there and it's dated uh 1128 for
the
1103 and quite frankly I'm not hugely
Keen to uh take all the shazzy apart
just to get in there and see the CRT but
it looks like a you know a reasonable
quality board in there as you'd expect
and nice and tidy on the wiring looms
and things like that so yeah it wasn't
just slapped together how you doing so
there you have it I hope you enjoyed
that look at the Apple Lisa 1983 vintage
31 years old or more um and it was
designed in the late 70s took him 5
years almost 5 years to get this thing
to Market absolutely incredible and then
it just flopped it was you know it
wasn't a bad machine at all it looked
the business and the gooey oper
operating system way ahead of its time
with lots of advanced memory protection
features and things like that that uh
you know a lot of things didn't come
around until um a decade or more later
so really Advanced machine for its time
but its price killed it that is why the
Apple Macintosh won because it was
targeted as a lower price machine and
when it came out it was it was very
wimpy as well kind of this thing was the
hardware was ultimately underpowered for
what it was trying to do same with the
original Macintosh but then the laser
printer came out and desktop publishing
and that's what sort of you know created
the success for the Apple Macintosh and
this thing is just a footnote in Apple's
history but anyway my hats off to all
the uh designers and software people who
worked on the Apple Lisa and ultimately
a total flop but I still like it doesn't
it look snazzy look at that gez I think
I'm obviously the boards in this
thing you could if you're a really Keen
Fanboy and had a lot of time and energy
on your hands you could repair the
boards and get it up and working in
original condition but who knows maybe I
could um uh run an emulator inside or
something like that drive the CRT
directly get it back working as an apple
Lisa but maybe not using the original uh
boards unfortunately I you know they're
I think they're probably a bit too far
gone and uh might not be worth
attempting to repair those and obviously
I can't power the thing up because it's
just not going to work it's not even
worth trying or because the edge
connectors on the cards are eaten away
and things like that so yeah really
requires substantial work just to get it
to a bootable condition let alone not
having a hard drive in the OS and
everything else so anyway if you got any
good ideas what I can do replace the CIT
and turn it into a fish tank maybe hm ni
sacr i' get haat mail death threats eh
what's the difference get those anyway
so hope you enjoyed that if you want to
discuss it e blog Forum links are down
below and as always if you liked tear
down Tuesday please give it a big thumbs
up cuz that helps on YouTube with the
search engine algorithms and all that
sort of crap anyway catch you next
time oh there it
is ah look at that thing of
beauty and for those who are curious
about the
famous signatures on the inside of the
case Yep they're all there check it out
and there folks
is Steve Jobs
tada